<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book>
	<bookinfo>
		<title>JA-SIG Central Authentication Service</title>
		<subtitle>Reference Documentation</subtitle>
		<releaseinfo>3.1-SNAPSHOT</releaseinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Scott</firstname>
				<surname>Battaglia</surname>
				<email>scott.battaglia@gmail.com</email>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Earl</firstname>
				<surname>Fogel</surname>
				<email>earl.fogel@usask.ca</email>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Arnaud</firstname>
				<surname>Lesueur</surname>
				<email>arnaud.lesueur@gmail.com</email>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
	</bookinfo>
	<toc></toc>
	
	<preface id="preface">
		<title>Preface</title>
		
		<para>JA-SIG Central Authentication Service provides an enterprise single sign on solution with an open and well-documented protocol, 
		a plethora of client libraries, and a Java server component.   As you will discover as you venture through this reference guide, we 
		have tried to provide you with a useful and highly configurable single sign on solution.
		</para>
	</preface>
	
	<part id="overall-architcture">
		<title>Overall Architecture</title>
		
		<partintro>
			<para>Like most software, CAS has certain central interfaces, classes, and conceptual abstractions that are commonly used 
			throughout the application.  In this part of the reference guide we will introduce CAS before examining these central elements 
			that are necessary to successfully planning and executing a CAS deployment.</para>
		</partintro>
		
		<chapter id="introduction">
			<title>Introduction</title>
			
			<sect1 id="what-is-cas">
				<title>What is CAS</title>
				<para>JA-SIG Central Authentication Service is an enterprise level, open-source, single sign on solutiion with a Java server 
				component and various client libraries written in a multitude of languages including PHP, PL/SQL, Java, and more.</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="history">
				<title>History</title>
				
				<para>The Central Authentication Service project began in 2001 at Yale University, initially developed by Shawn Bayern.  It 
				initially only supported 1-tier, centralized single sign on. In 2002, Yale released a new version of CAS (2.0) that provided 
				n-tier, proxiable, single sign-on.</para>

				<para>In September of 2004, Yale University and Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey held initial discussions about a 
				new version of CAS.  In December of 2005, CAS became a JA-SIG project.  Though the protocol did not change, CAS 3.0 
				introduced a completely new architecture that enabled deployers to easily extend and plug-in to the CAS server without 
				modifying the code.  This enabled new levels of sharing amongst deployers!  The architecture for CAS has not changed much 
				since its June 2005 release, and has allowed rapid development of new features and add-ons.</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="release-numbering">
				<title>Release Numbering</title>
				
				<para>It is useful to understand how CAS release numbers work, as it will help you identify he effort (or lack thereof) 
				involved in migrating to future releases of the project.  Officially, the CAS project uses teh Apache Portable Runtime 
				Project versioning guidelines, which can be viewed at <literal>http://apr.apache.org/versioning.html</literal>. We quote the 
				introduction contained on that page for your convenience:</para>
				
				<para><quote>Versions are denoted using a standard triplet of integers: MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH. The basic intent is that MAJOR 
				versions are incompatible, large-scale upgrades of the API. MINOR versions retain source and binary compatibility with older 
				minor versions, and changes in the PATCH level are perfectly compatible, forwards and backwards.</quote></para>
				
				<para>Note that we make every attempt for the CAS API to be perfectly compatible.  However, there have been a few instances
				in patch releases where we were upgrading libraries that were stabalizing their own APIs.  In those instances, CAS may not
				have been perfectly compatible.  In these few instances we will expend every effort to make the differences as apparent
				as possible.</para>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="technical-overview">
			<title>Technical Overview</title>
			
			<sect1 id="runtime-environment">
				<title>Runtime Environment</title>
				
				<para>CAS is written to execute within a standard Java 1.4 Runtime Environment.  It also supports Java 5.0, though it does not
				take advantage of any specific Java 5.0 features.  As CAS aims to operate in a self-contained manner, there is no need to 
				place any special configuration files into your Java Runtime Environment.  The only exception to this is if you are using a
				Java Authenticaton and Authorization Service (JAAS) policy file.</para>
				
				<para>Out of the box, CAS, with its example JSP pages, is designed to run on a container that supports the Servlet 2.4
				specification.  A good container is the Tomcat 5.x series, though any Servlet 2.4 will work.  In addition, by modifying the 
				JSP pages to use the old JSTL tags, one can get CAS to run on a Servlet 2.3 container such as Tomcat 4.x.  However, in many 
				cases it is not worth the effort.</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="shared-components">
				<title>Shared Components</title>
				
				<para>TODO</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="common-authentication">
				<title>Common Authentication</title>
				<para>TODO</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="common-conclusion">
				<title>Conclusion</title>
				<para>TODO</para>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
	
	</part>
	
	<part id="authentication">
		<title>Authentication</title>
		
		<partintro>
			<para>As a single sign on solution, CAS has no preference on what back-end authentication solution you use to authenticate your users.  Out of the box, CAS supports many different types of authentication including LDAP, database, X.509 Certificates, and JAAS.</para>
		</partintro>
		
		<chapter id="ldap">
			<title>LDAP Authentication Handlers</title>
			
			<sect1 id="ldap-dependencies">
				<title>Dependencies</title>
				<para>The JA-SIG LDAP Authentication Handlers depend on a few libraries:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>LdapTemplate - <literal>http://ldaptemplate.sf.net</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>JA-SIG LDAP Authentication Handler JAR  - <literal>${project.home}/target/cas-server-ldap-VERSION.jar</literal></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				
				<para>These required dependencies should be placed in the <literal>${project.homee}/localPlugins/lib</literal> directory.</para>				
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="ldap-core-classes">
				<title>Core Classes</title>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>FastBindLdapAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>This is the most straight-forward implementation of LDAP authentication. It simply tries to bind to the directory 
					with the credentials provided by the user. Since the user is not aware of the LDAP tree, you have to configure the 
					handler to try and bind to a certain preconfigured node. This means you can only use this method if you are able to 
					configure the user's node in advance. Else you'll need to use the search-and-bind method (explained below).</para>
					
					<para>The <literal>FastBindLdapAuthenticationHandler supports the following properties:</literal></para>
					
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><literal>filter</literal> - The filter property is the LDAP filter that will be used for the search. When constructing the filter, wherever you want the username to appear, place a "%u".</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>ignorePartialResultException</literal> - This property informs LdapTemplate to ignore PartialResultExceptions that may get thrown when connecting to an Active Directory.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>contextSource</literal> - This is a reference to a AuthenticatedLdapContextSource (see below) which will contain the settings for connecting to the LDAP server.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>BindLdapAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>This method first does a general search for the user before it tries to bind to the directory. When it finds the 
					user it attemps to do a bind with the DN that resulted from the search and the password from the user's submitted 
					credentials. Note that for this method you will need a special user that is allowed to search the directory (OR allow 
					anonymous access to search the directory).</para>
					
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><literal>filter</literal> - The filter property is the LDAP filter that will be used for the search. 
						When constructing the filter, wherever you want the username to appear, place a "%u".</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>ignorePartialResultException</literal> - This property informs LdapTemplate to ignore 
						PartialResultExceptions that may get thrown when connecting to an Active Directory.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>contextSource</literal> - This is a reference to a AuthenticatedLdapContextSource (see 
						below) which will contain the settings for connecting to the LDAP server.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>allowMultipleAccounts</literal> - </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>maxNumberOfResults</literal> - this is the maximum number of results we allow.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>scope</literal> - One of the predefined "SearchControl" Scopes: SearchControls.OBJECT_SCOPE,
						 SearchControls.ONELEVEL_SCOPE, or SearchControls.SUBTREE_SCOPE</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>searchBase</literal> - The search base is the node in the directory from where the search 
						will be performed.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>timeout</literal> - This is the amount of time we are willing to wait for the search 
						results to return.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>AuthenticatedLdapContextSource</title>
					<para>This class is an extension of LdapTemplate's LdapContextSource.  Its extended to allow it to retrieve specific 
					<literal>DirContext</literal>s while re-using existing environment settings.  Its additional method is modeled after the 
					Java <literal>DataSource</literal>.</para>
					<para>The LdapContextSource defines some important properties, listed below (note some of this is copied directly from 
					the JavaDocs):</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><literal>authenticatedReadOnly</literal> - Set to true if an authenticated environment should be 
						created for read-only operations.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>baseEnvironmentProperties</literal> - If any custom environment properties are needed, 
						these can be set using this method.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>password</literal> - Set the password (credentials) to use for getting authenticated 
						contexts.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>pooled</literal> - Set whether the pooling flag should be used.  Note that even if pooling 
						is set, the additional method provided by AuthenticatedLdapContextSource will not use pooling.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>url</literal> or <literal>urls</literal> - the url(s) to the LDAP server.  Specifying a list of servers automatically configures redundancy so it is highly recommended to do so.  Port 636 is the typical LDAP SSL port, 389 is the standard LDAP port. Java SDK v1.4.2+ interprets correctly ldap:// or ldaps:// without specifying the port. If you're using an older JDK you cannot specify the ldaps:// protocol so you'll need to explicitly define a port and set the protocol to SSL in the environment properties.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>userName</literal> - the username (principal) for getting authenticated contexts.</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>Please note that the JVM needs to trust the certificate of your SSL enabled LDAP server, else CAS will refuse to connect to your LDAP server. You can add the LDAP server's certificate to the JVM trust store ($JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/cacerts) to solve that issue.</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="ldap-configuration">
				<title>Configuration</title>
				
				<para>Note that all of the configuration items listed below should happen in the 
				<literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-INF/deployerConfigContext.xml</literal></para>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>Set up the AuthenticatedLdapContextSource</title>
					
					<para>Within the <literal>&lt;beans&gt;...&lt;/beans&gt;</literal>, place your AuthenticatedLdapContextSource bean.  
					Your configuration will look something like this:</para>
					
					<para>
						<programlisting>
		&lt;bean id="contextSource" class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.ldap.util.AuthenticatedLdapContextSource"&gt;
			&lt;property name="authenticatedReadOnly" value="true"/&gt;
			&lt;property name="password" value="{password_goes_here}"/&gt;
			&lt;property name="pooled" value="true"/&gt;
			&lt;property name="urls"&gt;
				&lt;list&gt;
					&lt;value&gt;ldap://ldap.rutgers.edu:636/&lt;/value&gt;
					&lt;value&gt;ldap://ldap2.rutgers.edu:636/&lt;/value&gt;
				&lt;/list&gt;
			&lt;/property&gt;
			&lt;property name="userName" value="{username_goes_here}"/&gt;
			&lt;property name="baseEnvironmentProperties"&gt;
				&lt;map&gt;
					&lt;entry&gt;
						&lt;key&gt;
							&lt;value&gt;java.naming.security.protocol&lt;/value&gt;
						&lt;/key&gt;
						&lt;value&gt;ssl&lt;/value&gt;
					&lt;/entry&gt;
					&lt;entry&gt;
						&lt;key&gt;
							&lt;value&gt;java.naming.security.authentication&lt;/value&gt;
						&lt;/key&gt;
						&lt;value&gt;simple&lt;/value&gt;
					&lt;/entry&gt;
				&lt;/map&gt;
			&lt;/property&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
						</programlisting>
					</para>
					<para>NOTE: You may or may not have all these properties set.  This is just an example.</para>
				</sect2>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>Set Up the *LdapAuthenticationHandlers.</title>
					<para>Both Ldap Authentication Handlers are set up in almost the same way (just different class names and properties), 
					so we're only going to show one here.</para>
					<para>This AuthenticationHandler is configured as a bean within the <literal>authenticationHandlers</literal> property 
					on the authenticationManager.  You'll most likely want to remove the test authentication handler there, and replace it 
					with this.</para>
					<para>
						<programlisting>
		&lt;bean class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.ldap.BindLdapAuthenticationHandler"&gt;
			&lt;property name="filter" value="uid=%u" /&gt;
			&lt;property name="searchBase" value="ou=people,dc=rutgers,dc=edu" /&gt;
			&lt;property name="contextSource" ref="contextSource" /&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
						</programlisting>
					</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="radius">
			<title>RADIUS Authentication Handlers</title>
			
			<sect1 id="radius-dependencies">
				<title>Dependencies</title>
				<para>The JA-SIG RADIUS Authentication Handlers depend on a few libraries:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>JRADIUS Client and Dictionary - <literal>http://jradius.sourceforge.net/</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>GNU Crypto - <literal>http://gnu.rtin.bz/software/gnu-crypto/#downloading</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>JA-SIG RADIUS Authentication Handler JAR  - <literal>${project.home}/target/cas-server-RADIUS-VERSION.jar</literal></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				
				<para>These required dependencies should be placed in the <literal>${project.homee}/localPlugins/lib</literal> directory.</para>				
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="radius-core-classes">
				<title>Core Classes</title>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>RadiusAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>The <literal>RadiusAuthenticationHandler</literal> is the class that will take your credentials and authenticate them against a RADIUS server.  It is able to handle two types of failovers: failover on an authentication failure, and failover on a server exception.  It can be configured with the following properties:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><literal>failoverOnAuthenticationFailure</literal> - boolean to determine whether we should try the next server if there is an authentication failure.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>failoverOnException</literal> - boolean to determine whether we should try the next server if an exception is thrown.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><literal>servers</literal> - takes an array of servers which are the RADIUS servers we would like to connect to. The handler tries them in the order they are configured.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>JRadiusServerImpl</title>
					<para>The <literal>JRadiusServerImpl</literal> is one implementation of the more generic <literal>RadiusServer</literal> interface.  Its underlying implementation relies on the JRADIUS library.  Each instance represents one RADIUS server and has various configuration options.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><literal>accountingPort</literal> - the accounting port that this server uses.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>authenticationPort</literal> - the authentication port this server uses.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>radiusAuthenticator</literal> - the RADIUS authenticator to use. Defaults to PAP.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>retries</literal> - the number of times to keep retrying a particular server.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>sharedSecret</literal> - the secret key used to communicate with the server.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>socketTimeout</literal> - the amount of time to wait before timing out.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><literal>hostName</literal> - the hostname of the RADIUS server.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="radius-configuration">
				<title>Configuration</title>
				
				<para>Note that all of the configuration items listed below should happen in the 
				<literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-INF/deployerConfigContext.xml</literal></para>
				
				<para>Below, you'll find an example configuration for two RADIUS servers and failoverOnException.  This authenticationHandler is configured within the "authenticationHandlers" property of the AuthenticationManagerImpl.  Usually, it would replace the test authentication handler.</para>
				<para>
				<programlisting>
	&lt;bean
		class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.radius.authentication.handler.support.RadiusAuthenticationHandler"&gt;
		&lt;property
			name="servers"&gt;
			&lt;list&gt;
				&lt;bean
					class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.radius.JRadiusServerImpl"&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="0" value="radius1.example.org" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="1" value="THIS_IS_MY_SHARED_SECRET" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="2"&gt;
						&lt;bean
							class="net.sf.jradius.client.auth.PAPAuthenticator" /&gt;
					&lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="3" value="AUTHENTICATION_PORT333" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="4" value="ACCOUNTING_PORT333" /&gt;
	
					&lt;constructor-arg index="5" value="SOCKET_TIMEOUT" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="6" value="NUMBER_OF_RETRIES" /&gt;
				&lt;/bean&gt;
				&lt;bean
					class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.radius.JRadiusServerImpl"&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="0" value="radius2.example.org" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="1" value="THIS_IS_MY_SHARED_SECRET" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="2"&gt;
						&lt;bean
							class="net.sf.jradius.client.auth.PAPAuthenticator" /&gt;
					&lt;/constructor-arg&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="3" value="AUTHENTICATION_PORT333" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="4" value="ACCOUNTING_PORT333" /&gt;
	
					&lt;constructor-arg index="5" value="SOCKET_TIMEOUT" /&gt;
					&lt;constructor-arg index="6" value="NUMBER_OF_RETRIES" /&gt;
				&lt;/bean&gt;
			&lt;/list&gt;
		&lt;/property&gt;
		&lt;property
			name="failoverOnException"
			value="true" /&gt;
	&lt;/bean&gt;
				</programlisting>
				</para>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="jaas">
			<title>JAAS Authentication Handlers</title>
			
			<para>Briefly, JAAS is a standard API provided by Java 1.4 and higher which provides PAM-like authentication and authorization. An external file is used to configure JAAS. Using JAAS with CAS allows modification of the authentication process without having to rebuild and redeploy CAS, and allows for PAM-style multi-module "stacked" authentication.</para>
			<para>Links</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>JAAS Reference Guide - <literal>http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/security/jaas/JAASRefGuide.html</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>JAAS Tutorial - <literal>http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/security/jaas/tutorials/</literal></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<sect1 id="jaas-dependencies">
				<title>Dependencies</title>
				<para>The JAAS Authentication Handler has no external dependencies.</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="jaas-core-classes">
				<title>Core Classes</title>
				<sect2>
					<title>JaasAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>The <literal>JaasAuthenticationHandler</literal> is a hook into the Java Authentication and Authorization Service and delegates all authentication to the underlying runtime and its configured JAAS file.  Therefore it only has one property:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><literal>realm</literal> - the realm within the JAAS configuration file we are going to use.  Defaults to CAS.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="jaas-configuration">
				<title>Configuration</title>

				<para>Note that all of the configuration items listed below should happen in the 
				<literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-INF/deployerConfigContext.xml</literal></para>
				
				<para>Like other handlers, the JAAS Authentication Handler is simply configured in the deployerConfigContext.xml.  Within the AuthenticationManager's "authenticationHandlers" property, place the following configuration (replacing the example Test handler):</para>
				<para>
				<programlisting>
		&lt;bean
			class="org.jasig.cas.authentication.handler.support.JaasAuthenticationHandler" /&gt;				
				</programlisting>
				</para>

				<sect2>
				<title>Example jaas.conf File</title>
				<para>Below, you'll find an example jaas.conf file which would contain your JAAS configuration information.</para>
				<para>A JAAS Configuration file is configured as a system property, i.e. -Djava.security.krb5.conf=/etc/krb5.conf</para>
				<para>
				<programlisting>
		/** 
		 * Login Configuration for JAAS.   First try Kerberos, then LDAP, then AD
		 * Note that a valid krb5.conf must be supplied to the JVM for Kerberos auth
		 *   -Djava.security.krb5.conf=/etc/krb5.conf
		 */
		CAS {
		  com.ibm.security.auth.module.Krb5LoginModule sufficient
			debug=FALSE;
		  edu.uconn.netid.jaas.LDAPLoginModule sufficient
			java.naming.provider.url="ldap://ldap.my.org:389/dc=my,dc=org"
			java.naming.security.principal="uid=cas,dc=my,dc=org"
			java.naming.security.credentials="password"
			Attribute="uid"
			startTLS="true";
		  edu.uconn.netid.jaas.LDAPLoginModule sufficient
			java.naming.provider.url="ldaps://ad.my.org:636/dc=ad,dc=my,dc=org"
			java.naming.security.principal="cas@ad.my.org"
			java.naming.security.credentials="password"
			Attribute="sAMAccountName";
		};		
				</programlisting>
				</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="cas">
			<title>Legacy CAS Password Handler Authentication Handler Adaptor</title>
			
			<para>Please note that though we support adapting CAS2 PasswordHandlers to CAS3 Authentication Handlers we recommend you upgrade to an Authentication Handler (especially since we have many generic solutions).</para>
			
			<sect1 id="cas-dependencies">
				<title>Dependencies</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Your original PasswordHandler</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>The cas-server-legacycas-VERSION.jar</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Original CAS2 jar</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>The jars should be placed in the localPlugins/lib directory.  All source code should be placed in the localPlugins/src directory.</para>
			</sect1>

			<sect1 id="cas-core-classes">
				<title>Core Classes</title>
				<sect2>
					<title>LegacyCasCredentials</title>
					<para>This class is an extension of the traditional CAS3 UsernamePasswordCredentials to include the HttpServletRequest, which all CAS2 password handler classes expect.</para>
				</sect2>
				<sect2>
					<title>LegacyCasCredentialsBinder</title>
					<para>The legacy binder allows for additional binding beyond the normal Spring request parameter/property binding.  In this case it sets the request property on the LegacyCasCredentials.</para>
				</sect2>
				<sect2>
					<title>LegacyCasPasswordHandlerAdaptorAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>This class basically extracts the properties from the LegacyCasCredentials and passes them to the PasswordHandler.</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="cas-configuration">
				<title>Configuration</title>
				
				<para>In your cas-servlet.xml, look for the <literal>AuthenticationViaForm</literal> bean, generally defined as follows:</para>
				<para>
				<programlisting>
		&lt;bean
			id="authenticationViaFormAction"
			parent="abstractCasLoginAction"
			class="org.jasig.cas.web.flow.AuthenticationViaFormAction" /&gt;
			</programlisting>
			</para>
			
			<para>Modify it so that it looks like this:</para>
			<para>
			<programlisting>
		&lt;bean
			id="authenticationViaFormAction"
			parent="abstractCasLoginAction"
			class="org.jasig.cas.web.flow.AuthenticationViaFormAction"&gt;
			&lt;property name="formObjectClass" value="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.cas.LegacyCasCredentials" /&gt;
			&lt;property name="formObjectName" value="credentials" /&gt;
			&lt;property name="credentialsBinder"&gt;
			&lt;bean
				class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.cas.LegacyCasCredentialsBinder" /&gt;
			&lt;/property&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
				</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>This configuration tells the FormAction to use the LegacyCasCredentials and the LegacyCasCredentialsBinder.</para>
				<para>Finally, in your deployerConfigContext.xml, you'll need to define your password handler.  In most cases you'll want to replace the existing test handler definition with the following:</para>
				
				<para>
				<programlisting>
          &lt;bean
              class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.cas.LegacyPasswordHandlerAdaptorAuthenticationHandler"&gt;
              &lt;property name="passwordHandler"&gt;
                  &lt;bean
                     class="edu.someschoool.its.cas.MySpecialPasswordHandler"/&gt;
              &lt;/property&gt;
          &lt;/bean&gt;
				</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>Note that <literal>edu.someschoool.its.cas.MySpecialPasswordHandler</literal> should be replaced with your 
				PasswordHandler class name.</para>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>

		<chapter id="spnego">
			<title>Spnego Authentication Handlers</title>
			
			<sect1 id="spnego-dependencies">
				<title>Dependencies</title>
				<para>The JA-SIG SPNEGO Authentication Handlers depend on a few libraries:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>The Java CIFS Client Library - <literal>http://jcifs.samba.org/</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The Java CIFS Extension Suite - <literal>http://sourceforge.net/projects/jcifs-ext/</literal></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>JA-SIG SPNEGO Authentication Handler JAR  - <literal>${project.home}/target/cas-server-support-spnego-VERSION.jar</literal></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect1>

			<sect1 id="spnego-core-classes">
				<title>Core Classes</title>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>JCIFSSpnegoAuthenticationHandler</title>
					<para>This is the implementation of an AuthenticationHandler for SPNEGO supports. This Handler support both NTLM and Kerberos. NTLM is disabled by default. This class supports the following properties:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><literal>principalWithDomainName</literal> - boolean to enable or disable domain name in the returned netid</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>NTLMallowed</literal> - allows to authenticate using SPNEGO/NTLM token</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>

				<sect2>
					<title>JCIFSConfig</title>
					<para>This class is the configuration helper for JCIFS and the Spring framework. This class supports the following properties:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><literal>jcifsServicePrincipal</literal> - set the Service Principal Name</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>jcifsServicePassword</literal> - set the password for the principal name</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>kerberosDebug</literal> - boolean to enable or disable the debug mode on Kerberos</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>kerberosRealm</literal> - set the Realm</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>kerberosKdc</literal> - set the KDC address</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>loginConf</literal> - path to the login.conf</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>

				<sect2>
					<title>SpnegoNegociateCredentialsAction</title>
					<para>First action of a SPNEGO flow : negociation. The server checks if the negociation string is in the request header:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>If found do nothing and return <literal>success()</literal></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>else add a WWW-Authenticate response header and a 401 response status, then return <literal>success()</literal></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</sect2>

				<sect2>
					<title>SpnegoCredentialsAction</title>
					<para>Second action of a SPNEGO flow : decode the gssapi-data and build a new <literal>SpnegoCredentials</literal>.</para>
					<para>Once <literal>AbstractNonInteractiveCredentialsAction</literal> has executed the authentication procedure, this action check wether a principal is present in Credentials and add correspondings response headers.</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>

			<sect1 id="spnego-configuration">
				<title>Configuration</title>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>Set up the Active Directory</title>
					<para>A service account should be created. This account is called a Service Principal Name account (SPN account).</para>
					
					<sect3>
						<title>Create the User</title>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>First start the <literal>Active Directory User and Computers</literal> from the <literal>Administration Tools</literal> menu.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Right click on the <literal>Users Repository</literal> and select <literal>New</literal> > <literal>User</literal></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Enter user information (by example <literal>myspnaccount</literal> for user login), press <literal>Next</literal>.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Enter the <literal>password</literal> and select <literal>Password never expires</literal> and click on <literal>Next</literal> and then on <literal>Finish</literal>.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>

					<sect3>
						<title>Modify the encryption algorithm</title>
						<para>We need to modify the user account in order to specify the encryption algorithm while RC4-HMAC is not supported by the Java GSS API. Open the newly created user account, select the <literal>Account</literal> tab. In the account options check <literal>Use DES encryption types for this account</literal> and click on <literal>OK</literal>. After this operation, the password must be reseted. To do so, right click on the user account and select the option <literal>Reset Password</literal>. Enter the <literal>password</literal> and press <literal>OK</literal>.</para>
						<para>Now that the user account has been created and updated, we need to create a service principal setting for the created user account. This is automatically handled by exporting a keytab file for the created account.</para>
					</sect3>

					<sect3>
						<title>Create the Keytab File</title>
						<para>The Keytab file enables a trust link between the CAS server and the Key Distribution Center (KDC). This file contains a cryptographic key. The ktpass tool, which comes from the Windows Resource Kit, is used to generate this file. In a console, enter the command:</para>
						<para><literal>ktpass.exe /out myspnaccount.keytab /princ HTTP/your.server.name.here@YOUR.REALM.HERE /pass * /mapuser myspnaccount /ptype krb5_nt_principal /crypto DES-CBC-MD5</literal></para>
						<para>This command will generate the myspnaccount.keytab file which has to be copied on the CAS server in order to test Kerberos from a bash using the MIT Kerberos V.</para>
					</sect3>

					<sect3>
						<title>Test the SPN account</title>
						<para>First configure MIT Kerberos V on the server. The file is <literal>/etc/krb5.conf</literal>. Here is an example :</para>
						<para>
							<programlisting>
		[logging]
		 default = FILE:/var/log/krb5libs.log
		 kdc = FILE:/var/log/krb5kdc.log
		 admin_server = FILE:/var/log/kadmind.log
		
		[libdefaults]
		 ticket_lifetime = 24000
		 default_realm = YOUR.REALM.HERE
		 default_keytab_name = /home/cas/kerberos/myspnaccount.keytab
		 dns_lookup_realm = false
		 dns_lookup_kdc = false
		 default_tkt_enctypes = des-cbc-md5
		 default_tgs_enctypes = des-cbc-md5
		
		[realms]
		 YOUR.REALM.HERE = {
		  kdc = your.kdc.your.realm.here:88
		 }
		
		[domain_realm]
		 .your.realm.here = YOUR.REALM.HERE
		 your.realm.here = YOUR.REALM.HERE
							</programlisting>
						</para>
						<para>Then verify that your are able to read the keytab file :</para>
						<para><literal>klist -k</literal></para>
						<para>Then verify that your are able to read the keytab file :</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><literal>kinit a_user_in_the_realm@YOUR.REALM.HERE</literal></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>klist</literal></para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>

				<sect2>
					<title>Set up Browser</title>
					
					<sect3>
						<title>Internet Explorer (min 5.01)</title>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>In Internet Explorer, click <literal>Internet Options</literal> on the <literal>Tools</literal> menu.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Click on the Advanced tab, click to select the <literal>Enable Integrated Windows Authentication (requires restart)</literal> check box in the <literal>Security section</literal>, and then click <literal>OK</literal>.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Click on the Security tab, click to select <literal>Local Intranet</literal> then click on <literal>Sites</literal>, then click on <literal>Advanced</literal>.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Enter <literal>https://your.server.name.here</literal> and validate by clicking on <literal>Add</literal> and <literal>OK</literal>.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><literal>Restart</literal> Internet Explorer.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>

					<sect3>
						<title>Firefox (min 0.9)</title>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>In Firefox, enter <literal>about:config</literal> as url and click on Go.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>On the line <literal>network.negotiate-auth.trusted-uris</literal>, right click on <literal>Modify</literal> and enter <literal>https://your.server.name.here</literal></para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
				
				<sect2>
					<title>Set up CAS</title>

					<sect3>
						<title>Set up the login webflow</title>
						<para>The CAS 3 Login Webflow needs to be modified. This webflow is located in <literal>/WEB-INF/login-webflow.xml</literal>. There are 2 new action states which are placed before the state <literal>viewLoginForm</literal>.</para>
						<para>
							<programlisting>
		&lt;action-state id="startAuthenticate"&gt;
		  &lt;action bean="negociateSpnego" /&gt;
		  &lt;transition on="success" to="spnego" /&gt;
		&lt;/action-state&gt;
		
		&lt;action-state id="spnego"&gt;
		  &lt;action bean="spnego" /&gt;
		  &lt;transition on="success" to="sendTicketGrantingTicket" /&gt;
		  &lt;transition on="error" to="viewLoginForm" /&gt; 
		&lt;/action-state&gt;
							</programlisting>
						</para>
						<para>And 2 existing transitions need to be update :</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>In the decision-state <literal>gatewayRequestCheck</literal>, replace reference to <literal>viewLoginForm</literal> by <literal>startAuthenticate</literal></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>In the decision-state <literal>renewRequestCheck</literal>, replace reference to <literal>viewLoginForm</literal> by <literal>startAuthenticate</literal></para></listitem>						
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>

					<sect3>

						<sect4>
							<title>/WEB-INF/cas-servlet.xml</title>
							<para>Two beans are needed for the login flow. Those beans are :</para>
							<para>
								<programlisting>
		&lt;bean id="negociateSpnego" class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.web.flow.SpnegoNegociateCredentialsAction"&gt; 
			&lt;property name="ticketGrantingTicketCookieGenerator" ref="ticketGrantingTicketCookieGenerator"/&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
		
		&lt;bean id="spnego" class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.web.flow.SpnegoCredentialsAction"&gt; 
			&lt;property name="centralAuthenticationService" ref="centralAuthenticationService"/&gt;
			&lt;property name="ticketGrantingTicketCookieGenerator" ref="ticketGrantingTicketCookieGenerator"/&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
								</programlisting>
							</para>
						</sect4>

						<sect4>
							<title>/WEB-INF/deployerConfigContext.xml</title>
							<para>In the bean <literal>authenticationManager</literal>, add :</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><literal>org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.authentication.principal.SpnegoCredentialsToPrincipalResolver</literal> as <literal>credentialsToPrincipalResolvers</literal></para></listitem>
								<listitem><para><literal>org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.authentication.handler.support.JCIFSSpnegoAuthenticationHandler</literal> as <literal>authenticationHandlers</literal></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
							<para>
								<programlisting>
		&lt;bean id="authenticationManager" class="org.jasig.cas.authentication.AuthenticationManagerImpl"&gt;
		  &lt;property name="credentialsToPrincipalResolvers"&gt;
		    &lt;list&gt;
		      &lt;!--  ... the others credentialsToPrincipalResolvers ... --&gt;
		      &lt;bean class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.authentication.principal.SpnegoCredentialsToPrincipalResolver" /&gt;
		    &lt;/list&gt;
		  &lt;/property&gt;
		  &lt;property name="authenticationHandlers"&gt;
		    &lt;list&gt;
		      &lt;bean class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.authentication.handler.support.JCIFSSpnegoAuthenticationHandler"&gt;
		        &lt;property name="authentication"&gt;
			  &lt;bean class="jcifs.spnego.Authentication" /&gt;
		        &lt;/property&gt;
			&lt;property name="principalWithDomainName" value="false" /&gt;
		        &lt;property name="NTLMallowed" value="true"/&gt;
		      &lt;/bean&gt;
		      &lt;!--  ... the others authenticationHandlers... --&gt;
		    &lt;/list&gt;
		  &lt;/property&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
								</programlisting>
							</para>
							<para>There is also the <literal>jcifsConfig</literal> bean which needs to be added.</para>
							<para>
								<programlisting>
		&lt;bean name="jcifsConfig" class="org.jasig.cas.adaptors.spnego.authentication.handler.support.JCIFSConfig"&gt;
		  &lt;property name="jcifsServicePrincipal" value="HTTP/your.server.name.here@YOUR.REALM.HERE" /&gt;
		  &lt;property name="jcifsServicePassword" value="the.service.password.here" /&gt;
		  &lt;property name="kerberosDebug" value="false" /&gt;
		  &lt;property name="kerberosRealm" value="YOUR.REALM.HERE" /&gt;
		  &lt;property name="kerberosKdc" value="THE.KDC.IP.HERE" /&gt;
		  &lt;property name="loginConf" value="/path/to/WEB-INF/login.conf" /&gt;
		&lt;/bean&gt;
								</programlisting>
							</para>							
						</sect4>
						
						<sect4>
							<title>/WEB-INF/login.conf</title>
							<para>Copy or create the file <literal>/path/to/WEB-INF/login.conf</literal></para>
							<para>
								<programlisting>
		jcifs.spnego.initiate {
		    com.sun.security.auth.module.Krb5LoginModule required storeKey=true;
		};
		jcifs.spnego.accept {
		    com.sun.security.auth.module.Krb5LoginModule required storeKey=true;
		};
								</programlisting>
							</para>
						</sect4>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>

		</chapter>

<!-- 
		<chapter id="x509">
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="database">
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="trusted">
		</chapter>
 -->			
	</part>
	
	<part id="deploying">
		<title>Deploying CAS</title>
		<chapter id="configuration">
			<title>Basic CAS Configuration</title>
			<sect1 id="initial-setup">
				<title>Initial Setup</title>
				
				<para>If you don't have Java installed on your machine, the first step is to download Java.  Though CAS works under Java 
				1.4, we recommend Java 1.5. You can download Java 1.5 from the Sun Web Site 
				<literal>http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/download.jsp</literal>.  Next, be sure to obtain a servlet container.  One easy to 
				use servlet container is Apache Tomcat, downloadable here: <literal>http://tomcat.apache.org/</literal>.  We recommend the 
				latest 5.5.x release.</para>
				
				<para>Next, download and unzip/untar the latest CAS release.  You may want to try everything out by taking the demo CAS war
				file and placing it within the TOMCAT_HOME/webapps folder.  Once you've done that, start up Tomcat: TOMCAT_HOME/bin/start.sh 
				or TOMCAT_HOME/start.bat depending on your operating system.  Then try and access CAS (http://localhost:8080/cas/login).  
				If everything works, then you've set it up correctly.</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="logging">
				<title>Logging</title>
				<para>By default CAS includes log4j.  However, you can remove that and use whatever you want (as long as Commons Logging 
				supports it).  This section assumes you're still using log4j.</para>
				<para>The log4j configuration file is located in <literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-NF/classes/log4j.properties</literal>.  
				By default logging is set to INFO for ja-sig code and WARN for Spring code.  While debugging you may want to set those to 
				DEBUG.  When in production though, you probably want to run them both as WARN.  Depending on your needs, it may make sense 
				to keep the defaults (INFO and WARN).</para>
			</sect1>
			
			<sect1 id="spring-config">
				<title>Spring Configuration Files</title>
				<para>CAS utilizes Spring as its IOC container, thus there are some Spring XML configuration files.  For the most part, you 
				do no need to modify these except in the case where you are adding authentication handlers (see the Authentication Handler 
				section).</para>
				<para>By default, CAS includes internationalized message resource bundles, located in the 
				<literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-INF/classes</literal> directory.  In many cases you do not need to touch these.  
				However, if your organization has specific requirements, you may need to edit the text contained within the ones for you 
				appropriate language(s).</para>
				<para>Finally, in <literal>${project.home}/webapp/WEB-INF/classes</literal> directory, there is also a 
				default_views.properties file.  You probably don't want to edit that, so make a copy of it.  In that file, you'll reference 
				your custom JSP pages (see below) for each type (i.e. th login page).  In the cas-servlet.xml, you'll want to edit the 
				viewResolver bean's "baseName" property to point to your file.</para>
			</sect1>				
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="view-customization">
			<title>Customizing the Views</title>
			<para> TODO</para>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="building">
			<title>Building the WAR</title>
			<para>Building the war file is very easy.  All you'll need is Apache's Ant.  With Ant installed, navigate to 
			<literal>${project.home}/localPlugins</literal> and execute "ant war".  This should generate a war file in the 
			<literal>target</literal> directory that you can then deploy.</para>
		</chapter>
		
		<chapter id="deploying-war">
			<title>Deploying</title>
			<para>In most cases, you can take the war file that you generated in the previous step, drop it in the webapps folder, and start 
			up your container.  Please note the requirements for the container (one that satisfies the Servlet 2.4 spec).</para>
		</chapter>	
	</part>
</book>