<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to Jasig under one or more contributor license
  ~ agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work
  ~ for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ Jasig licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
  ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file
  ~ except in compliance with the License.  You may obtain a
  ~ copy of the License at the following location:
  ~
  ~   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
  ~ under the License.
  -->

<chapter xml:lang="en" xml:id="architecture" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ./schemata/docbook.xsd"
  version="5.0">

  <title>Architecture</title>

  <para>The CAS architecture can be described in terms of system components
    including the clients and server that communicate via supported protocols.
    </para>


  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="media/architecture.png" format="PNG" align="left" contentwidth="320pt" contentdepth="400pt"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <section xml:id="system_components">
    <title>System Components</title>
    <para>The CAS server and clients comprise the two physical components of
      the CAS system architecture that communicate by means of various protocols.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>CAS Server</title>
      <para>The CAS server application is Java servlet built on the Spring Framework whose primary responsibility is
          to authenticate users and grant access to CAS-enabled services, commonly called CAS clients, by issuing and
          validating tickets. An SSO session is created when the server issues a ticket-granting ticket (TGT) to the
          user upon successful login. A service ticket (ST) is issued to a service at the user's request via browser
          redirects using the TGT as a token. The ST is subsequently validated at the CAS server via back-channel
          communication. These interactions are described in great detail in the
          <link xlink:href="http://www.jasig.org/cas/protocol">CAS Protocol document</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CAS Clients</title>
      <para>The term "CAS client" has two distinct meanings in its common use. A CAS client is any CAS-enabled
          application that can communicate with the server via a supported protocol. A CAS client is also a software
          package that can be integrated with various software platforms and applications in order to communicate with
          the CAS server using or or more supported protocols. CAS clients supporting a number of software platforms
          and products have been developed.
      </para>

        <section>
            <title>Software Platforms</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Apache httpd Server (via the mod_auth_cas module)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Java (via the Jasig Java CAS Client)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.NET (via the .NET CAS Client)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PHP (via phpCAS)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Perl (via PerlCAS)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Python (via pycas)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ruby (via rubycas-client)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Applications</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Outlook Web Application (via ClearPass Extension and .NET CAS Client)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Atlassian Confluence (via a plugin)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Atlassian JIRA (via a plugin)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Drupal (via a module)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Liferay (via built-in support)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>uPortal (via built-in support)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>When the term "CAS client" appears in this manual without further qualification, it refers to the
          integration components such as the Jasig Java CAS Client rather than to the application relying upon
          (a client of) the CAS server.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="protocols">
    <title>Protocols</title>
    <para>Clients communicate with the server by any of several supported
      protocols.  All the supported protocols are conceptually similar, yet some have features or characteristics
        that make them desirable for particular applications or use cases. For example, the CAS protocol supports
        delegated (proxy) authentication, and the SAML protocol supports attribute release and single sign-out.</para>

    <section xml:id="cas_protocol">
      <title>CAS Protocol</title>
      <para>The CAS protocol is a simple and powerful ticket-based protocol developed exclusively for CAS. The CAS
          protocol has two general versions, version 1 is a simple text-based protocol, while version 2 is an XML-based
          protocol that supports a novel form of delegated authentication called "proxy authentication." CAS is one of
          the few SSO products to support this kind of feature. A complete protocol specification, including versions 1
          and 2, may be found at
          <link xlink:href="http://www.jasig.org/cas/protocol">http://www.jasig.org/cas/protocol</link>.</para>
        <note>
            <title>CAS protocols shared across CAS software versions</title>
            <para>The CAS 3.4 server software speaks the CAS 1 and CAS 2 protocols.  Integrations with CAS via the CAS
            protocol should be independent of particular versions of the CAS server software.  That is, client libraries
            should work with CAS, not merely work with some particular version of the CAS server software, by virtue
            of these protocols remaining unchanged across CAS 2 and CAS 3 versions.  CAS server 3.4 (which this manual
            documents) speaks the same CAS protocol that CAS 3.3, 3.2, 3.1, 3.0, and even Yale CAS Server 2 versions
            speak, and so client libraries shouldn't need to or even be able to differentiate among these.</para>
            <para>Additional features not originally in the CAS protocol have been added (such as single logout
            callbacks), but support for the CAS protocol as defined remains.</para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="saml11_protocol">
      <title>SAML1.1 Protocol</title>
      <para>CAS provides limited support for the SAML 1.1 protocol. SAML support was adopted to leverage a standardized protocol for two important use cases:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Attribute release, where attributes describe the authenticated principal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Single sign-out (via callbacks to particpating applications advising them of single sign-on
                        session termination).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="saml2_protocol">
      <title>SAML2 Protocol</title>
      <para>CAS provides limited support for the SAML2 protocol.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="openid_protocol">
      <title>OpenID Protocol</title>
      <para>The CAS server has limited support for the OpenID identity provider functionality, which allows integration
          with applications and services such as Google Apps and Salesforce.com. The OpenID protocol spefication is
          maintained as a set of specifications for different protocol aspects that can be found at
          <link xlink:href="http://openid.net/developers/specs/">http://openid.net/developers/specs/</link>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>Server Software Components</title>
      <para>
      In order to facilitate discussion of configuration and deployment in following chapters, it is helpful to provide
          an overview of server software components. CAS server software components are described in terms of Java
          interfaces that form an API that organizes the application source code and provides configuration and
          extension points for deployers. The following sections discuss the core interfaces of the CAS server API.
      </para>
      <section>
          <title>Authentication</title>
          <para>
           CAS supports two distinct notions of authentication, user and service authentication. For the purposes of
           this user manual, "authentication" means user authentication where a user presents some credential(s) to be
              validated. The service authentication process will be referred to as an "access." There are a number of
              components that deal with user authentication that are described in detail in the following sections.
          </para>
          <section>
              <title>Authentication Handlers</title>
              <para>
              The AuthenticationHandler interface describes the contract by which users present credentials for
                  validation and simply return a boolean true/false value for success/failure. Authentication handlers
                  are the integration point with identity management systems including directories and databases.
              </para>
          </section>
          <section>
              <title>Authentication Managers</title>
              <para>
              The AuthenticationManager interface describes the strategy by which AuthenticationHandlers will be
                  evaluated to determine authentication success or failure.
              </para>
          </section>
          <section>
              <title>Principals</title>
              <para>
              A principal describes an authenticated user, including a unique identifier over one or more identity
                  management systems. The principal may also contain arbitrary attributes describing the user, such as
                  display name and security groups. These attributes are commonly used to facilitate authorization and
                  personalization in CAS client applications.
              </para>
          </section>
          <section>
              <title>Credential-to-Principal Resolvers</title>
              <para>
              Upon successful authentication, CAS leverages CredentialsToPrincipalResolver components to attempt to map
                  credential attributes onto a principal. A common use case is to map the username of a
                  username/password pair onto an email address or other distinct namespace that is needed or expected
                  by CAS client applications.
              </para>
          </section>

          <section>
              <title>Principal Name Transformers</title>
              <para>
              The PrincipalNameTransformer interface allows customization of the provided user name prior to
                  authentication. A common use case of this component is to add a domain suffix to the username such
                  that a fully-qualified username will be used to perform authentication.
              </para>
          </section>
          <section>
              <title>Authentication Meta Data Populators</title>
              <para>
              The AuthenticationMetaDataPopulator interface supports adding arbitrary meta data to the CAS
                  authentication event. A common use case would be to store the authentication method or level of
                  assurance of the user's credential.
              </para>
          </section>
          <section>
              <title>Authentication Workflow</title>
              <para>
                  The CAS authentication workflow is not an interface per se, but is a workflow implemented in Spring
                  WebFlow that can be customized to support novel use cases. Customizing logical transitions, decision
                  points, and start/end states is straightforward and can generally be done by editing XML, while
                  defining new actions typically requires development of actions in Java.
              </para>
          </section>
      </section>

      <section>
          <title>Security Policy</title>
          <para>
          CAS provides a number of configurable and extensible components to control various aspects of security policy
              including SSO session timeouts, cryptographic strength of tickets/identifiers, and
              pre-authentication/post-authentication actions.
          </para>

          <section>
              <title>Services Registry</title>
              <para>The ServiceRegistry component is responsible for defining the allowed services that may request
                  and validate tickets provided by CAS as well as other service-specific concerns:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Authorization to perform delegated authentication (proxy)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Attribute release policy</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Whether or not service can participate in single sign-on (non-participating services can
                        still use CAS for user login, but the user will be prompted to authenticate on each login to
                        the service)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Selection of per-service UI theme
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </section>

          <section>
              <title>Ticket Expiration Policy</title>
              <para>The TicketExpirationPolicy component defines the lifecycle policy for various types of tickets.
                  Common expiration policies are supported including finite timeout expiration, sliding scale
                  expiration, expiration exceeding N uses, and everlasting tickets. The policy contract is simple to
                  facilitate development of custom policies.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
              <title>Identifier Generators</title>
              <para>
                There are a number of generator interfaces that specify the generation of various identifiers:
              </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NumericGenerator - Generates sequential integer identifiers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>RandomStringGenerator - Generates random string identifiers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>UniqueTicketIdGenerator - Generates unique identifiers for use in tickets</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </section>

          <section>
              <title>Handler Interceptors</title>
              <para>
              CAS supports the use of the Spring HandlerInterceptor component to instrument certain operations such as
                  authentication and ticket validation. CAS leverages this component to implement security policies
                  such as login throttling, although other security policies could easily be developed.
              </para>
          </section>
      </section>
      <section>
          <title>Ticket Registry</title>
          <para>
          The TicketRegistry component is a ticket storage abstraction layer. CAS supports a number of implementations
              out of the box where all except the default in-memory storage are suitable for HA environments:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Memory - DefaultTicketRegistry (default)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Database - JpaTicketRegistry</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Memcached - MemCacheTicketRegistry</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>JBoss Cache - JBossCacheTicketRegistry</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
      </section>
  </section>
</chapter>