<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to Jasig under one or more contributor license
  ~ agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work
  ~ for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ Jasig licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
  ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file
  ~ except in compliance with the License.  You may obtain a
  ~ copy of the License at the following location:
  ~
  ~   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
  ~ under the License.
  -->

<chapter xml:lang="en" xml:id="hardening" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ./schemata/docbook.xsd
http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink "
         version="5.0">

    <title>Hardening your CAS Server</title>

    <para>Jasig CAS is security software and can provide secure Web-based single sign on reducing the
        proliferation of end user password exposures, improving both the reality and your confidence
        in the reality of security considerations in your environment.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="must-use-ssl">
        <title>Use SSL</title>
        <para>This should probably go without saying, but: yes, you have to use SSL.  Really.  No, you can't just run
        CAS over http:// .  It won't be okay.  And yes, your CAS-using service needs to use SSL too, or else
        authenticated sessions with it can be hijacked.  Really.  You have to use SSL.  CAS ships not using SSL
        for ease of getting started with and trying out CAS, but your real production CAS implementation must
        use SSL.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="if-not-using-proxy-tickets">
            <title>If you aren't using Proxy Tickets</title>
        <para>Proxy Tickets are a powerful, important, and potentially security-improving feature of the CAS
            single sign-on solution. You can use them to good effect in place of replaying end-user credentials
            or plenipotent service credentials that do not require participation in an end-user single sign-on session.
        </para>
        <para>However, Proxy Tickets carry risk in that services accepting proxy tickets are responsible for validating
            the
            proxy chain (the list of services through which the end-user's authentication have been delegated to arrive
            at
            the ticket validating service). Services can opt out of accepting proxy tickets entirely (and avoid
            responsibility for validating proxy chains) by simply validating tickets against the /serviceValidate
            validation endpoint, but experience has shown it's easy to be confused about this and configure to
            unintentionally use the /proxyValidate endpoint yet not scrutinize any proxy chains that appear in the
            ticket validation response.
        </para>
        <para>If your CAS environment is not (yet?) intending to make use of proxy tickets, consider
            un-mapping the /proxyValidate endpoint in your CAS server to prevent services from accidentally
            choosing to accept proxy tickets. Note that if you run a decentralized CAS server then you may not know
            whether and what services are making use of proxy tickets.
        </para>
        <para>Historically any service could obtain a Proxy Granting Ticket
            and from it a Proxy Ticket to access any other service. That is, the security model is decentralized rather
            than centralized. You can centralize some of this through the Services Registry, by restricting which
            services
            are allowed to obtain proxy tickets, such that if you're careful to restrict all registrations from
            being allowed to acquire proxy tickets. This is one option for disabling proxy tickets.
        </para>
        <para>However, you may sleep better at night if you disable the /proxyValidate endpoint outright. This is easy
            to do. Simply add <filename>/WEB-INF/cas-servlet.xml</filename> to your local CAS project if it's
            not there already, and then comment out or delete this element:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
          &lt;prop
            key=&quot;/proxyValidate&quot;&gt;
            proxyValidateController
          &lt;/prop&gt;
        </programlisting>
        <para>However, some versions of the phpCAS client library require the /proxyValidate endpoint even when only
        service tickets are accepted.  If you simply remove the /proxyValidate mapping, this client library won't
        work with your CAS server and that may be annoying.  Instead of removing the /proxyValidate endpoint outright,
        you could map it to the <emphasis>serviceValidateController</emphasis> behavior:</para>
        <programlisting>
          &lt;prop
            key=&quot;/proxyValidate&quot;&gt;
            serviceValidateController
          &lt;/prop&gt;
        </programlisting>
        <para>This will have the effect of making your /proxyValidate endpoint behave as /serviceValidate and reject
        all proxy tickets.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>