<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Licensed to Jasig under one or more contributor license
  ~ agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work
  ~ for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  ~ Jasig licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
  ~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file
  ~ except in compliance with the License.  You may obtain a
  ~ copy of the License at the following location:
  ~
  ~   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  ~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  ~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  ~ KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  ~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
  ~ under the License.
  -->

<chapter xml:lang="en" xml:id="planning" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook ./schemata/docbook.xsd"
         version="5.0">

    <title>Planning and Deployment</title>

    <para>Planning a CAS deployment requires consideration of the application and
        platform ecosystem in light of security considerations, availability, and
        capacity.</para>

    <section>
        <title>System Integration</title>
        <para>
            Enterprise deployment planning begins with careful consideration of existing software and systems to be
            integrated with CAS including applications, identity management and authentication services, and other
            supporting enterprise services.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>CAS Client Integration</title>
            <para>The following CAS clients can be employed to integrate most proprietary and
                open source applications:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Java CAS Client</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>.NET CAS Client</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>mod_auth_cas module for Apache</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>phpCAS</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                Additionally, custom applications developed in common languages/platforms are easily supported in most
                cases. In almost all cases Web applications are easily integrated with CAS. Difficulty commonly arises,
                however, with applications built on legacy frameworks such as database procedural languages (e.g. PL/SQL)
                or mainframe applications. These kinds of applications frequently require creative solutions for CAS
                integration, but there are many such examples in community-contributed integration solutions that
                showcase the flexibility of CAS.
            </para>
            <para>
                The following matrix summarizes popular applications and the required libraries for CAS integration.
            </para>
            <table>
                <title>Popular applications to CASify and the CAS Client integration software libraries employed
                    in these integrations</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">


                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Application or Framework</entry>
                            <entry>CAS Client</entry>
                            <entry>Supportedness</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Outlook Web Access / Outlook Web Application</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client and ClearPass Extension</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.
                                ClearPass is a community-supported CAS extension that is not part of the CAS server
                                itself.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Apache httpd</entry>
                            <entry>mod_auth_cas</entry>
                            <entry>mod_auth_cas is a core vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>ASP.NET</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>IIS7</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client</entry>
                            <entry>.NET CAS Client is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Java Servlets</entry>
                            <entry>Jasig Java CAS Client</entry>
                            <entry>Jasig Java CAS Client is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Spring Security</entry>
                            <entry>Spring Security and the Jasig Java CAS Client</entry>
                            <entry>Spring Security is not vended by Jasig, but CAS server depends out of the box on
                                Spring Security's CAS support for authenticating administrators to access the CAS
                                Services Registry functionality.
                                The Jasig Java CAS Client is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>PHP applications</entry>
                            <entry>phpCAS</entry>
                            <entry>
                                phpCAS is a core supported vended-by-Jasig CAS integration module.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Ruby on Rails</entry>
                            <entry><link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/rubycas-client/">rubycas-client</link></entry>
                            <entry>
                                rubycas-client is not vended by Jasig.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Perl</entry>
                            <entry><link xlink:href="http://sourcesup.cru.fr/projects/perlcas/">PerlCAS</link></entry>
                            <entry>
                                PerlCAS is not vended by Jasig.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>

            </table>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>Authentication</title>
            <para>CAS must be integrated with one or more enterprise authentication systems such as LDAP/Active Directory.
                While it is most common to integrate CAS with a single enterprise authentication system, it is possible to
                integrate with multiple systems given the following important requirement.</para>

            <caution>
                <title>Using Multiple Authentication Sources</title>
                <para>The namespaces of each authentication source must be guaranteed to be unique in order to prevent
                    ambiguity about the identity of the authenticating user. In particular neither a credential such as a
                    username nor the name of the resolved principal may exist in more than one authentication source.</para>
            </caution>

            <para>CAS supports many ways of authenticating user credentials, including:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>validation against Active Directory, either via LDAP or Kerberos protocol</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>JAAS (whereby CAS supports Kerberos)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>RDBMS / JDBC (database)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LDAP</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>RADIUS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SPNEGO</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>REMOTE_USER (Container authentication)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>X.509 Certificates</para>
                </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Attribute Release</title>
            <para>
                In addition to authenticating the user, CAS is capable of querying for additional attributes about a user
                following authentication in order to store and release some or all of this information to requesting
                services for the purposes such as authorization and personalization. Attribute data is commonly sourced
                from the same store as authentication data, but the design of attribute retrieval allows configuring
                multiple disparate attribute sources.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Supporting Services</title>
            <para>Many enterprises have services that may be leveraged by CAS. For example, the availability of enterprise
                database hosting might suggest the use of JpaTicketRegistry for the server ticket store. Likewise clustering
                hardware or software might be used by CAS for improved availability and/or capacity.</para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Security Considerations</title>
        <para>CAS deployment requires consideration of enterprise security concerns such as integration with IDM
            software, PKI, and security policy.</para>
        <para>
            TODO: complete this Security Considerations section.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Availability and Capacity Planning</title>
        <para>Every enterprise deployment of CAS should be vitally concerned with availability and performance
            obtained through careful capacity planning.</para>
        <para>
            TODO: complete this Availability and Capacity Planning section.
        </para>
    </section>

     <section>
        <title>Deployment Scenarios</title>
        <para>We present some popular deployment scenarios for CAS with commentary on availability and performance characteristics.</para>
        <para>
            TODO: complete this Deployment Scenarios section.  E.g. &quot;Single Client/Single Server&quot;
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>